Sebastián

Bustamante Jaramillo

Curriculum Vitae



I am a physicist with a strong interest in astrophysics, specifically in cosmology. I have always thought humanity's understanding the large-scale universe through science is like a bacteria colony trying to build a complete map of the earth or even more. I am looking forward to cooperate and get involved with high quality research teams in order to contribute my humble grain of sand to this grand and exciting enterprise called science. If I were asked to introduce myself in four words, they would be astrophysics-programming-swimming-guitar.

GENERAL INFORMATION

Jame Sebastián Bustamante Jaramillo.

Date of Birth 20th June, 1990.

Place of Birth Maceo - Colombia.

Nationality Colombian.

Marital Status Single.

Identification c.c. 1128400433.

Address Avenida 21 # 57 AA 65, Bello - Colombia.

 $\begin{array}{lll} \textbf{Home tel.} & +057 \ (4) \ 4820138 \ . \\ & \textbf{Mobile} & +057 \ 3108992409 \ . \\ & \textbf{e-mail} & \text{macsebas} 33@\text{gmail.com}. \end{array}$

Inst. e-mail sbustama@pegasus.udea.edu.co.

EDUCATION

2001-2006 High School Diploma, Institución Educativa Cisneros, Cisneros, Colombia.

2007-2012 B.Sc. in Physics, Physics Institute, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Thesis "The place of the Milky Way and Andromeda in the cosmic web".

Description This study is aimed to characterize the local environment of Local Group (LG)-like systems from dark matter simulations of the large-scale universe. Using two different types of simulations, an unconstrained simulation (Bolshoi project) and a set of constrained simulations (CLUES project), it

unconstrained simulation (Bolshoi project) and a set of constrained simulations (CLUES project), it is first constructed a LG-like sample based upon observational constrains on the kinematic properties and isolation criteria of the real LG, along with the results of the CLUES simulations. By using a tensorial scheme based upon the peculiar velocity field of the dark matter, the V-web scheme, it is classified the local environment of systems in each simulation. Finally, it has been found that LG-like systems lies preferentially in sheet-like regions, furthermore a significant environmental bias for the total mass and the specific energy. No correlations have been found for the specific angular momentum and other studied properties.

Advisor Jaime E. Forero-Romero, Ph.D.

Additional Education

2008 Extension Course in Planetary Sciences, Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

FIELDS OF INTEREST

Cosmology. Large-scale structure formation. Galaxy astrophysics. Planetary interior. Numerical simulations. Computational astrophysics. General astrophysics and physics. Programming.

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native speaker.

English Good.

Computer Skills

Linux, MSWindows. Systems

Development C/C++, Python, Basic, TI Basic, shell scripts.

Software Mathematica, LaTeX, gnuplot, Gadget.

Tools N-body simulations, SPH, MonteCarlo, Finite Differences, Numerical integrators, Audio processing.

Repositories A list of my projects can be found in my github page: https://github.com/sbustamante.

Honours, Awards, and Accomplishments

2006 The best graduate of the promotion, Institución Educativa Cisneros, Cisneros, Colombia.

2007/II Honour Roll, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

2009/I Honour Roll, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

2009/II Honour Roll, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

2012 First Best Oral Presentation, Il International Congress of Astrobiology, Medellín, Colombia.

TEACHING

Assistant Physics 1 (Newtonian Mechanics), 2013/I, Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences, Universidad Instructor de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Assistant Computational Complement of Physics 2 (Electricity and Magnetism), 2013/I, Faculty of

Instructor Exact and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Assistant Computational Complement of Physics 3 (Oscillations and Waves), 2013/I, Faculty of Exact

Instructor and Natural Sciences, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

Adjunct Introductory Physics, 2013/II, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín,

Colombia. **Professor**

Adjunct Laboratory of Physics 1 (Newtonian Mechanics), 2013/II, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad

Professor de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2010-2011 Young Investigator Programme, Fundamental of quantum mechanics, Group of Atomic and Molecular Physics (GFAM), Committee for Research Development (CODI), Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín. Colombia.

2011-2012 Young Investigator Programme, Thermal evolution of rocky exoplanets, Group of Computational Physics and Astrophysics (FACom), Committee for Research Development (CODI), Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia.

August, 2012 Research Internship, Physics Department, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia.

PUBLICATIONS

The influence of thermal evolution in the magnetic protection of terrestrial planets, J.I. Zuluaga, **S. Bustamante**, P.A Cuartas, J.H. Hoyos, The Astrophysical Journal, ApJ 770 23, 2013.

The kinematics of the Local Group in a cosmological context, J.E. Forero-Romero, Y. Hoffman, **S. Bustamante**, S. Gottloeber, G. Yepes, The Astrophysical Journal Letters, ApJL 767 L5, 2013.

Habitability in binary systems, P.A. Mason, J. Clark, P.A. Cuartas, J.I. Zuluaga, **S. Bustamant**e, American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting # 222, # 302.05, 2013.

Habitability in binary systems: the role of UV reduction and magnetic protection, J. Clark, P.A. Mason, J.I. Zuluaga, P.A. Cuartas, **S. Bustamante**, American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #222, #217.03, 2013.

PARTICIPATION IN EVENTS

(Poster) **PLYNET, Python Planetary Physics Package**, *II Colombian Congress of Astronomy and Astrophysics*, Bogotá, Colombia, 2010.

(Oral presentation) **Thermal evolution of rocky exoplanets**, *III International Congress of Formation and Modelling in Basic Sciences*, Medellín, Colombia, 2011.

(Oral presentation) **Numerical modelling of the interior and thermal evolution of habitable planets**, *II International Congress of Astrobiology*, Medellín, Colombia, 2012.

(Oral presentation) **The place of the Local Group in the cosmic web**, *III Colombian Congress of Astronomy and Astrophysics*, Bucaramanga, Colombia, 2012.

REFERENCES

 Jaime E. Forero-Romero (Former Advisor)
 Assistant Professor, Physics Department, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia. je.forero@uniandes.edu.co

Juan Carlos Muñoz-Cuartas

Assistant Professor, Physics Institute, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, Colombia. juancarlosmunozc@gmail.co

Carlos A. Vera-Ciro

Postdoctoral Researcher, Department of Astronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin, United States.

ciro@astro.wisc.edu